So today's דף Daf is טז Tet Zayin and we pick up
with גופא. Gufa. It is six lines down from the top of
the דף Daf and the discussion had been about
the משנה Mishna had mentioned using the legs of a bed for
סכך Schach and assumed that those were מקבל טומאה. Mekabel Tumah.
And the גמרא Gemara got into a question: How are detached legs
from a bed susceptible for טומאה? Tumah? They're not part of a
it's just wood and wood needs a receptacle and it's not even
part of a vessel anymore. So it related to a debate where
in a משנה Mishna in כלים Kelim about a broken bed or
a bed taken into parts, not broken because that can talk about
a disassembled bed, and that there's an opinion that it actually even
in a disassembled state or partially disassembled state could still become טמא
Tamei because it's going to be reassembled as תוספות Tosafot points out
and because it can somewhat be used in its current state. And
that would be the case that we'd be talking about with half
of a bed with two legs attached. So that's just explaining the
משנה. Mishna.
Now however the גמרא Gemara suggested a very different explanation. Different explanation
the גמרא Gemara suggested is not that now it can become טמא,
Tamei, but since it once was a vessel, it remains considered for
laws of סוכה Sukkah invalid סכך, Schach, meaning it's no longer able
to become טמא Tamei if it's a broken vessel or detached or
no longer usable, but maybe it still remains invalid סכך Schach because
of its history. Maybe that just labels it for life. So that
now is the issue the גמרא Gemara is going to turn to.
So let's take a look. גופא, Gufa, let's go back to the
original statement and look at it in greater focus. אמר
רב אמי בר טביומי, Amar Rav Ami bar Tavyumi, so this is
what רב אמי בר טביומי Rav Ami bar Tavyumi said: סככה בבלאי
כלים, Skacha bivlei kelim, if you used worn out vessels or worn
out clothing as the גמרא Gemara will explain it, פסולה, Psula, it's
still invalid even though these are no longer able—susceptible for טומאה Tumah
because they're no longer wearable or usable, they're no longer הלכה Halakhically
considered a vessel. Nevertheless it was once a vessel and it was
once a clothing and therefore it remains invalid. מאי בלאי כלים? Mai
bivlei kelim? What do you mean by that? What's the, be a
little more precise. So it says, אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: מטלניות, Matlaniyot,
like rags, שאין בהם שלש על שלש, She'ein bahem shalosh al shalosh,
that are not even three fingers width by three fingers width, ולא
חזיין לא לעניים ולא לעשירים, V'lo chazyian lo l'aniyim v'lo l'ashirim, they're
not fit
either—not only for wealthy people wouldn't use them, even poor people wouldn't
use them. What does this mean? What is the minimum size of
a piece of cloth that's considered to be usable and therefore מקבל
טומאה? Mekabel Tumah? So the גמרא Gemara actually has three different measures.
One is שלשה על שלשה Shlosha al shlosha טפחים, Tefachim, which is
basically like a foot by a foot or a little bit less,
let's say nine inches by nine inches. The other is שלש על
שלש Shalosh al shalosh fingers, which is about, I don't know, an
inch and a half, two inches by two inches. And it says
that the bigger size, if you're wealthy, anything less than שלשה על
שלשה Shlosha al shlosha you throw out. So for you it stops
being a vessel. But for a poor person, they're going to use
the smaller size. What are they going to use it for? They're
going to use it for patching, you know, they'll patch up their
clothing. So but so therefore anything smaller than שלשה על שלשה Shlosha
al shlosha they'll still use. What they won't use is something that's
smaller than שלש על שלש Shalosh al shalosh fingers. That's already so
small, nobody would use it. Again this becomes very interesting,
the gendered לשון Lashon of the Hebrew language and the
thankfully the fact that the some of the different measurements switch between
זכר Zakhar and נקבה. Nekeva. So when the גמרא Gemara talks about
these things, it will talk about שלש על שלש Shalosh al shalosh
or שלשה על שלשה, Shlosha al shlosha, which is very different. שלשה
על שלשה Shlosha al shlosha is three טפחים Tefachim by three טפחים,
Tefachim, because טפח Tefach is masculine, so it's שלשה, Shlosha, the number
in the sort of reverse from the gender of the word. שלשה
על שלשה Shlosha al shlosha means three טפחים Tefachim by three טפחים.
Tefachim. Here we're talking about a very small piece, שלש על שלש,
Shalosh al shalosh, three fingers width by three fingers width, and that
is so small nobody would use it. So even though we're at
a stage that you've got a piece of cloth that is so
small nobody would use it and therefore under no measure would it
be considered a vessel, nevertheless it is still פסול Pasul for סכך
Schach because it once was considered a כלי, Keli, once was considered
clothing. Okay so that's a very important הלכה Halakha for הלכות סכך
Hilkhot Schach that you can't even use broken vessels or things that
once were כלים. Kelim.
So the גמרא Gemara now says, right? And you could imagine scenarios
like that, like I said, you're walking by the street and somebody's
thrown out their garbage and there's a whole broken up table into
pieces of wood, oh and great, it's סוכה Sukkah time, you gather
up some of the wood, right? So it actually is a problem
based on this teaching. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this:
תני
כוותיה דרב אמי בר טביומי, Tni kevati d'Rav Ami bar Tavyumi, we
taught similar to רב אמי בר טביומי. Rav Ami bar Tavyumi.
מחצלת של שיפא, Machatzat shel shaifa, if you have a mat of
שיפא Shaifa of גמי, Gemi, of different types of different types of
like of material, I don't know how they translate it, I didn't
look it up, but one is like a weave or
a rushes.
Sedge
or rush, okay,
papyrus and reed grass.
Papyrus, reeds, right, some type of a reed, a wicker, a wicker
mat. Okay, what's the הלכה? halacha?
שייריה אף על פי שנפחתו משיעורה אין מסככין בהם. she-reha af al
pi she-nifchasu mi-shiurah, ein mesachachin ba-hem. So if you have sort of
the remnant of it, so like if it's a little leftover piece
of mat, it broke up and you're left over with a little
section of mat, even though it's smaller than the שיעור, shiur, meaning
the normal שיעור shiur here, not a שיעור shiur for סכך, schach,
but a שיעור shiur for טומאה. tumah. Okay, the normal size for
טומאה tumah that you need, that you need for a mat to
be considered a vessel and usable for טומאה tumah is six טפחים
tfachim by six טפחים, tfachim, which is pretty big. It's like a
foot and a half by a foot and a half. Okay, a
mat smaller than that you don't use. So even though you've got
this remnant of a mat and it's smaller than the size for
being a vessel for טומאה tumah and it's not fit for becoming
טמא, tamei, אין מסככין בהם, ein mesachachin ba-hem, you still cannot use
it for סכך. schach. So basically the exact same הלכה halacha for
clothing applies now to a vessel to a mat. You have a
mat, it started off the size of a big enough mat to
become טמא. tamei. Now it's so small that it cannot. Nevertheless, you
cannot use this piece of it because it originated from a vessel
even though now it is no longer susceptible for טומאה. tumah.
מחצלת הקנים matzeles ha-kanim now that we're talking about this, if you
have a mat made out of like sticks or reeds, reeds I
should say, גדולה מסככין בה, gedolah mesachachin ba, if it's big you
can use it for סכך, schach, קטנה אין מסככין בה, ktanah ein
mesachachin ba, if it's small you can't. Now that should strike you
as ironic because until now we've been talking about the larger the
size, the more it's considered a vessel, the more it's considered to
be able to become טמא. tamei. But this is actually a larger
discussion we're gonna have in a few days, which is, and this
is extremely important, cause now everybody uses these סכך schach mats. You
know, you roll up these סכך schach mats. And well, is that
a, is that מקבל טומאה? mekabel tumah? Now I mean you could
use one of those things before they started making them, you know,
large scale for סוכה succah purposes, you could go into your Home
Depot and get a similar type of a bamboo mat. Now what
would those be sold for? What would people use those bamboo mats
for? So often they'd use it for sitting, sometimes they might use
it for a wall like for a screen but they might use
it for sitting. So that's the question. If you have a mat,
do we say that it's a כלי, kli, it's made for sitting,
and therefore it's מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah, or do we say it's
made more for like putting on your roof, putting up on a
wall and therefore not a כלי kli and therefore not מקבל טומאה?
mekabel tumah? So the גמרא gemara says it depends on the size.
A small size, you know, sort of big enough for one human's
tush or maybe two or three or whatever, you know, that's a
mat. When it gets to be very large, people don't use it
for a sitting mat, they use it for a wall, they use
it for a roof, and therefore it's not מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah
and therefore it's כשר. kosher. It's quite fascinating the bigger it is
in this case the more it defines it as a different type
of a thing, not a vessel but a piece of you know
structure, and therefore not מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah and therefore acceptable. Okay
so that's the point, גדולה מסככין בה, gedolah mesachachin ba, a big
one you can use it, קטנה אין מסככין בה, ktanah ein mesachachin
ba, small one you cannot. רבי אליעזר אומר אף היא מקבלת טומאה
ואין מסככין בה, Rabbi Eliezer omer, af hi mekabeles tumah ve-ein mesachachin
ba, even a big one I disagree with you, it's usable as
a mat for sitting on and therefore it can become,
it's fit for becoming טמא tamei and therefore it cannot be used
as כשר kosher סכך. schach. So more of that later but the
upshot for us is that once something started as a vessel, it
remains invalid for סכך schach even though it is no longer a
vessel. And now we go to the second part of the משנה
mishna which is digging out a סוכה succah from a haystack, and
you wind up with walls and with a roof made out of
hay, so it should be okay but the thing is you never
put the roof on, the roof got made sort of by itself
indirectly when you removed the inside of the haystack and that is
the classic problem of תעשה ולא מן העשוי. taaseh velo min ha-asuy.
You have to make the סוכה, succah, it can't somehow be pre-made,
you know made you know sort of indirectly not through a direct
act of being made and again סוכה succah here refers to the
סכך. schach. So let's take a look. אמר רב הונא לא שנו,
Amar Rav Huna, lo shanu, this is, we only taught that this
was a problem, אלא שאין שם חלל טפח, ela she-ein sham chalal
tefach, that it did not begin with a space with a volume
of a טפח, tefach, with a cavity of a טפח, tefach, במשך
שבעה be-meshech shiva going the length of seven by seven טפחים tfachim
which is the minimum size of
a סוכה. succah. אבל יש שם חלל טפח במשך שבעה הרי זו
סוכה, Aval yesh sham chalal tefach be-meshech shiva, harei zu succah, it
is a סוכה. succah. What does that mean?
It means the משנה mishna is talking about
your standard case, the standard case is you've got a haystack, it's
all hay,
and you come along right and you're gonna hollow out you know
your סוכה succah from it and take it out and you've made
the סכך schach indirectly by hollowing that out. Okay but let's say
that it didn't, when it started it didn't start as all hay.
It was all hay here but it started and you had for
some reason. And it's hard to imagine exactly what the scenario is
that you've created this, you know, how physically this happened, maybe you
put the hay on top of some type of a chest, or
something.
I have a picture here, it's on top of a platform.
Okay, right. So you had some type of a platform and you
dumped your haystack on top of it. So here in the סוכה,
sukkah, you've already started with
a cavity of seven by seven טפחים tefachim and one טפח tefach
high. And then you put the haystack on top of it. So
now the question is when you initially put the haystack on top
of it, maybe you did the making of the סכך schach because
you put the סכך, schach, you put the hay on top of
a cavity that's the size of a סוכה sukkah area, but the
problem is it's only a height of one טפח. tefach. So is
that making the סכך? schach? Because now it's over an area of
one טפח. tefach. And when you finish it, you're just fixing up
the walls. Or do we say that doesn't yet count as סכך?
schach? Because סכך schach it has to be higher than ten טפחים.
tefachim. It has to be over the height of a סוכה. sukkah.
And he is saying that that actually does count as סכך. schach.
In this case, if you have something that's this and you put
the סכך schach on this type of an area, seven by seven
by one, you made סכך schach of a סוכה sukkah because now
a טפח tefach of one as we know is considered an אהל
ohel like a tent, like a roof for purposes of טומאה. tumah.
So therefore it actually is making something that is considered סכך. schach.
And the fact that it's not high enough, okay, that's a problem
with the walls of a סוכה, sukkah, it's a problem with the
dimensions of the סוכה, sukkah, but it's not a סכך schach problem.
You have כשר kosher סכך schach on a not high enough סוכה.
sukkah. Okay, so let's take a look at that גמרא. Gemara. אבל
יש שם חלל טפח במשך שבעה הרי זה סוכה Aval yesh sham
challal tefach bemeshech shivah harei zeh sukkah that is
valid. תניא נמי הכי Tanya nami hachi similarly, החוטט בגדיש לעשות לו
סוכה הרי זה סוכה. Hachotet begadish laasot lo sukkah harei zeh sukkah.
We have a ברייתא Baraita that teaches the opposite of our משנה.
Mishnah. It says it's כשר, kosher, הרי זה סוכה. harei zeh sukkah.
So the גמרא Gemara says והאנן תנן אינה סוכה, Veanan tnan einah
sukkah, our משנה Mishnah teaches it's no good. So rather than saying
it's a debate, אלא לאו שמע מינה, ela lav shema mina, it
must be here's the reconciliation: כרב הונא, keRav Huna, like רב הונא,
Rav Huna, that the ברייתא Baraita that says it is good is
talking about that it started with, it's so funny to leave out
that tiny little detail which is so bizarre, but okay. It's talking
about a scenario where it started by seven by seven by one
high. And then it's כשר, kosher, you made an act of making
כשר kosher סכך schach and then you finish by digging out the
rest of it. You obviously have to dig out the rest of
it. You need ten טפחים tefachim by ten טפחים, tefachim, but you
started by an act of כשר kosher סכך. schach.
שמע מינה, Shema mina, that's a good proof. איכא דרמי לה מירמי,
Ika d'rami lei mirmei, some say that רב הונא Rav Huna's statement
didn't start as a commentary to the משנה, Mishnah, it started by
dealing with the contradiction. What was the contradiction? תנן, Tnan, our משנה
Mishnah says החוטט בגדיש לעשות לו סוכה אינה סוכה. Hachotet begadish laasot
lo sukkah einah sukkah. If you dig out, it's not a סוכה.
sukkah. והתניא Vehatanya
הרי זה סוכה, harei zeh sukkah, we have a ברייתא Baraita that
says it is. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, so comes רב
הונא Rav Huna to say I got the answer. לא קשיא, Lo
kashya, it's not difficult. כאן שיש שם חלל טפח במשך שבעה, Kan
sheyesh sham challal tefach bemeshech shivah, if you started with a hollow
of a טפח tefach by seven by seven. Then you made a
כשר kosher סכך schach and then just dig out the rest
to make it ten high. כאן שאין שם חלל במשך שבעה, Kan
she'ein sham challal bemeshech shivah, the משנה Mishnah is talking about there
was no hollow to begin with and therefore your act of digging
out was an act of creating סכך, schach, but it was indirect
and therefore it's תעשה ולא מן העשוי. ta'aseh velo min ha'asui. There's
a very nice little תוספות Tosafot that does a, you know, some
thing that אחרונים Acharonim like to do is say לשיטתיה, leshitateih, like,
oh, often they say it by the ראשונים, Rishonim, they say, you
know, this ראשון, Rishon, you know, who says this in this גמרא
Gemara is going to take the same approach in another גמרא Gemara
and you see how these ideas are all connected. Which is okay,
that makes sense. People should have consistent ideas across different areas. But
it's fun to see where ideas like connect and their consistent applications
of the same idea. Here תוספות Tosafot does that by an opinion
of an אמורא. Amora. If you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot,
he says אבל יש שם חלל טפח, Aval yesh sham challal tefach,
four lines down in the wide lines, he says משכחת למימר רב
הונא לטעמיה. Mashkachat lemeimar Rav Huna letaameih. We could say that רב
הונא, Rav Huna, who says it's כשר kosher סכך schach when it's
over an area of one טפח tefach high, is going to base
according to the reason he said earlier. דאמר לעיל, Deamar le'eil, he
said like about six days ago,
גבי בין סוכה לסוכה טפח. gabi bein sukkah lesukkah tefach. Remember we
had the הלכה halachic question of a סוכה sukkah on top of
a סוכה. sukkah. Two סכך. schachs. And the question was how high
does separate does the second סכך schach have to be from the
first so it can get that identity of an independent סכך schach
and be defined as a סכך? schach? And guess what? רב הונא
Rav Huna said once it's a טפח tefach higher it's already defined
as סכך schach and therefore it's the problem of סוכה sukkah under
a סוכה. sukkah. So just look at that. רב הונא Rav Huna
is consistent. He says that once it's a טפח tefach high it
already has the identity of סכך. schach. Not necessarily the סוכה sukkah's
כשר kosher yet, but it has an identity of סכך. schach. Okay.
And then he says ושמא מאן דאמר התם ארבע הכא מודה דלאו
שמואל דאמר התם עשרה הכא לא שייך. Veshama man deamar hatam arba
hacha modeh delav Shmuel deamar hatam asara hacha lo shayach. So תוספות
Tosafot points out that it's not, you know, you could be more
מחמיר machmir there than you are here. I mean, let's say שמואל
Shmuel there says ten טפחים. tefachim. But שמואל Shmuel says why do
you need ten טפחים? tefachim? Because שמואל Shmuel says it's not enough
to say סכך schach under a סכך. schach. You have to say
סוכה sukkah under a סוכה. sukkah. So תוספות, Tosafot, okay, you know,
שמואל Shmuel in theory could agree here because here... There it's an
idea of סוכה succa you need ten טפחים, tefachim, here it's an
idea of סכך schach maybe he would agree. So it's interesting connecting
those two debates and then he deals with the four טפחים tefachim
which is more complicated. But the interesting point is the same רב
הונא Rav Huna who there said it gets an identity of סכך
schach when it's one טפח tefach removed, here too says it gets
that identity, you made a kosher סכך schach and now you just
have to finish the walls. Okay, this by the way gets to
this question that was asked the other day about תעשה ולא מן
העשוי ta'aseh v'lo min he'asuy about when you put let's say you
put kosher סכך schach on top of your סוכה succa frame before
making the walls, right? Is that תעשה ולא מן העשוי? ta'aseh v'lo
min he'asuy? You made it before the walls were before the walls
were up. So that actually is debated in the אחרונים. achronim. This
גמרא Gemara makes it sound very clear that it should be okay
because this גמרא Gemara is almost the same reality. You had kosher
סכך schach and the way it's being framed is that the walls
weren't high enough, the walls weren't ten טפחים, tefachim, they were one
טפח tefach walls. You finish making them into ten טפח tefach walls
and it's fine once you put up the once right so the
סכך schach could be put up before you have the full walls.
That's certainly what this גמרא Gemara seems to be saying, so that
should make it okay. You might want to make a distinction, at
least here you have the beginning of a wall, you have a
one טפח tefach wall as opposed to the frame you don't have
a beginning of a wall at all. But anyway, it is a
interesting question about you know do you when you put up the
סכך schach do the walls have to be kosher? This גמרא Gemara
certainly says even if the walls are just one טפח tefach you
can finish the walls afterwards. Yes.
סכך schach has to shade most of the sun, in this case
סכך schach is shading all of it.
Right, so we discussed that. What defines the סכך schach to be
so thick and permanent that it's no longer סכך? schach? So תוספות
Tosafot basically said it is not the fact that it lets in
sunlight, it's based on another גמרא Gemara it's the fact that it
lets in rain. So I would think a haystack would let in
rain. Okay, so yes. Aren't you technically raising סכך schach
so wouldn't it be the same way that you say?
So you are... so you're correct because in this case right what's
going to wind up being the סכך schach at the end is
going to be this space over here. This stuff here isn't going
to be the סכך. schach. But in a way you could say
fine but when you put this whole you know this whole mound
of hay over it, all of this was סכך, schach, it was
very thick סכך. schach. So even though you're removing the bottom part
of סכך, schach, all of this was סכך schach over the one
טפח tefach area and you're still keeping the top part and that
was also initially סכך. schach. Right, when we say you have a
טפח tefach area you put this on, we're saying all of this,
not just the bottom layer, all of this is kosher סכך schach
and then you remove the middle section. But right, but that would
be okay. רש''י Rashi compared it by the way to the case
where you might remember before in the גמרא Gemara you had a
nine טפח tefach סוכה succa and then what you did what you
did was you dug a hole here in the floor right and
made it ten טפחים. tefachim. So there too he says look, you
start the סכך schach can be kosher and the walls finished later,
right? So that's what happened here too, the סכך schach was kosher
and then the height was finished later which means they became walls
halachically after the סכך schach was put on.
Then you don't have to do that ritual of raising it.
Oh, oh raising it and putting it down? Correct because it was
put up kosher when it was put up.
That's the whole point. So it's fine even if you just do
the סוכה succa with
the סכך schach
before the walls
and then you put up the walls. According to this it would
seem that the most obvious direct application of this to a case
of putting it on the סכך schach first and then the frame
is you would not have to lift up the סכך schach again.
Okay, you might want to make a distinction if it started with
a טפח tefach wall as opposed to starting with no wall, but
the simple application of this is is that you can have you
can do the making of the סכך schach before there's any wall
before there's a wall. Okay, so let's take a look now at
but you know I would first put up your walls before your
סכך. schach. Okay,
don't get into a מחלוקת, machloket, alright, but that's the anyway he
brought that's what this גמרא Gemara seems to be concluding. Let's take
a look now at the next
משנה. mishna. המשלשל Hamshalshel דפנות, dfanot, talking about walls, if you are
lowering down your walls, right, imagine you basically have like a curtain
that you hang up near the top of the סכך schach and
you lower it down. Okay, so that's המשלשל hamshalshel is the word
for lowering down. You're... but starting מלמעלה למטה, milmala l'mata, you start
at the top and you lower your walls down towards the floor,
the walls down, אם גבוה מן הארץ שלושה טפחים פסולה. im gavoha
min ha'aretz shlosha tefachim pesula. So this is an idea we know
we've heard of. If it is more than three טפחים tefachim removed
from the floor, it is invalid. Why? Because you cannot say לבוד.
lavud. Within three טפחים tefachim it's like it's connected, three טפחים tefachim
or more, I shouldn't say more than three טפחים, tefachim, three טפחים
tefachim or more,
it's no longer considered attached to the ground and you need your
wall to be attached to the ground. Okay, it's interesting by the
way that it seems to be just a straight application of the
לבוד lavud principle, but there are places where the גמרא Gemara specifically
also refers to its inability to function as a מחיצה mechitza because
it says three טפחים tefachim or more גדיים gedayim goats can go
underneath it. And that's interesting, there's also sort of to makes it
a specific מחיצה mechitza idea and not just a general לבוד lavud
idea, like if it can't even stop animals from running under it
you can't call it a wall. Okay, but more simply it's a
simple application of the
לבוד lavud idea.
Right, right, exactly, is the same discussions in ערובין. Eruvin. Okay, so
that so it has to be attached to the ground it has
to be within three טפחים tefachim of the ground. Now מלמטה... milmata...
Let's say you're building your wall from the floor up and it
also has to reach the סכך. s'chach. אם גבוה עשרה טפחים, im
gavoah asara tefachim, once it's ten טפחים tefachim high, it's כשר. kosher.
It doesn't have to touch the סכך. s'chach. Why not? Even though
it does in principle have to touch the סכך, s'chach, or this
is, that's the normal way it's understood, then in principle it has
to touch the סכך. s'chach. You've got here, okay, this is a
very common case in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, you've got here your
סכך. s'chach. Your סכך s'chach is up here, but your walls
are only, you know, only at the bottom. Right? Right? Is it
כשר kosher or not?
The גמרא Gemara says once these are ten טפחים tefachim it's כשר.
kosher.
Okay, you got your סוכה succah scenario, that's not a סוכה succah
that's a סוכה, succah, that's supposed to be the poles so they
are. Okay, so why is it כשר? kosher? So you could say,
because you could theoretically say, the walls don't have to reach the
סכך. s'chach. You've got כשר kosher סכך, s'chach, your כשר kosher walls,
they're under the סכך, s'chach, right? So it's not like they're not
under the סכך. s'chach. Maybe that's enough? Maybe it's under the סכך
s'chach is enough? If it's higher than three טפחים, tefachim, it can't
be called a מחיצה mechitzah because things can get through it. Once
it's connected to the ground and it's within three טפחים, tefachim, and
it can be called a מחיצה, mechitzah, and you have a כשר
kosher מחיצה, mechitzah, under the סכך s'chach it's okay. That's normally what
you would have said, or I don't know, you might have said
that. The גמרא Gemara though you might remember has the idea of
the, what I call, well the גמרא Gemara calls it גוד אחית
Gud Achis
and גוד אסיק. Gud Assik. Just to remind you these are the
classic what I call the magic principles of סוכה succah and דופן
עקומה. dofen akuma. The דופן עקומה dofen akuma you remember, I call
the magic bending wall. If you have פסול pasul סכך, s'chach, you
look at your סכך s'chach as a continuation of your wall. These
are the magic extending walls. Okay, so גוד אחית, Gud Achis, by
the way it's interesting what the word גוד Gud means. רש"י Rashi
says the word גוד Gud means to stretch, but also גוד Gud
also sometimes means a wall. Okay, so anyway, so
גוד אחית מחיצתא. Gud Achis mechitzta. So anyway, so it means stretch
your wall down or take your wall or have your wall go
down, or גוד אסיק, Gud Assik, your wall stretches up. So this
is the magic, right, you know, you know, extending wall down and
this is the same one for the magic extending wall up. So
once you say you have a מחיצה, mechitzah, then you can say
גוד אסיק Gud Assik and we envision the מחיצה mechitzah going all
the way up. And that's why it doesn't have to touch the
סכך. s'chach. Not that in principle it doesn't have to touch, which
would have been one way of saying it. In principle it has
to, right, be adjacent to the סכך. s'chach. The only problem is,
the way you do it is by saying you imagine the wall
going up. Now, the astute person will say, one minute, if you
can imagine the wall once you have ten טפחים tefachim going up
and it doesn't have to be close to the סכך, s'chach, go
ahead what are you going to say?
Right, what was the problem in the beginning of the משנה? mishnah?
Let it be less than, let it be more than three
טפחים, tefachim, you've got a ten טפח tefach wall, let it extend
down. Well guess who says that? The next opinion. רבי יוסי אומר
כשם שמלמטה למעלה עשרה טפחים, Rabbi Yossi omer kesheim she'mimalta lemaala asara
tefachim, the same way ten טפחים tefachim is enough from the ground
and it doesn't have to reach the סכך, s'chach, כך מלמעלה למטה
עשרה טפחים. kach mimaala lemata asara tefachim. Once you get ten טפחים
tefachim going down, right, you have מחיצה mechitzah and then imagine it
continuing to extend down. The rabbis disagree. The rabbis say it doesn't
start to be called a מחיצה mechitzah unless it is the basic
idea of a מחיצה mechitzah is a wall at the ground level.
That's the basic concept of a מחיצה, mechitzah, not a suspended wall
in mid-air. So it only gets an identity of a מחיצה mechitzah
once it's connected to the ground. Once it's a מחיצה, mechitzah, then
it can extend up. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi disagrees. רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi says any ten טפחים tefachim of some horizontal plane is a
מחיצה, mechitzah, and therefore even if it is high, it can go,
you know, down, it can go down to the, it can be
high up the ground. Interesting question according to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
and we'll get to this, is can you do this twice? Right,
let's say according to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi you had your wall
like this. Could you extend it both up and down? But anyway
he allows you to go down as well as up. The rabbis
say no there's a difference. It has to start by being connected
to the ground. Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. במאי קמיפלגי? bimai kamifligi? What's the debate about? מר סבר מחיצה
תלויה מתרת, mar savar mechitzah teluya matheres, one holds that a suspended
מחיצה mechitzah makes the space
allowable, ומר סבר מחיצה תלויה אינה מתרת, umar savar mechitzah teluya einah
matheres, it does not make it allowable. Now, the word מתרת matheres
is a strange word, right? You would have said is a מחיצה,
mechitzah, you would have said maybe is מכשיר, machshir, makes it a
good סוכה. succah. What's the word מתרת? matheres? So the point is
this is a debate that is borrowed or an issue, a language
that is borrowed from הלכות שבת hilchos Shabbos because the other major,
one of the other major places that מחיצה mechitzah matters is in
the גמרא Gemara is in הלכות שבת. hilchos Shabbos. A space that's,
you know, has מחיצות mechitzos ten טפחים tefachim high, is a רשות
היחיד, reshus hayachid, you know, three walls, three and a four, how
ever many and it's a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. Right? So that
is, so what let's say you have a suspended מחיצה, mechitzah, high
off the ground, can you carry in the space below? Is the
space below רשות היחיד reshus hayachid or not? So there is a
debate of מחיצה תלויה מתרת. mechitza teluya materes. The word מתרת materes
comes from that discussion. Will it make the space within the מחיצות
mechitzas permissible, meaning a private domain for שבת? Shabbos? But the גמרא
Gemara is assuming at the end of the day it's the same
debate. Does it count as a מחיצה mechitza or not? If it
counts as a מחיצה mechitza for שבת, Shabbos, it should count for
סוכה Sukkah vice versa. The גמרא Gemara will question that in a
minute, but now we are assuming that it's the same question here
would be the question by שבת. Shabbos. Is a מחיצה תלויה מתרת?
mechitza teluya materes? Does it make the space permissible? And now we're
going to see that debate. תנן התם, Tenan hasam, we taught over
there in
עירובין. Eruvin. בור שבין שתי חצירות אין ממלאין הימנו בשבת. Bor she-bein
shtei chatzeiros ein memalin mimenu be-Shabbos. If you have a well between
two courtyards and each courtyard has made a separate עירוב eiruv and
you cannot carry from one courtyard to the next, so and
but unfortunately that's okay, fine, don't carry from one courtyard to the
next, but you got a well that's on the borderline between the
two courtyards and it's in the space of both of the courtyards
and so don't fill your water from it on שבת, Shabbos, because
even though the well's a רשות
היחיד, reshus hayachid, what's the scenario?
The scenario is
here's courtyard one,
right? Here's all the houses, right?
You didn't know you had to take drawing 101 for the
דף היומי. Daf Yomi. And here's courtyard number two. Okay, right, this
I should have drawn it in a different color. Anyway, okay, fine,
whatever. And right here, and they have walls around them, right? So
there's walls that make it a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. All right,
but right here in the space between the courtyard one and two
is a well. I'm going to make this circle look more like
a well. And don't go ahead and draw water from it on
שבת Shabbos because why? Because you'll be taking stuff from the other
courtyard. Right, you're not allowed to carry from one courtyard to the
next because there's no עירוב eiruv between the two; each one made
their own עירוב, eiruv, each one is a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid,
they're separate רשויות היחיד. reshuyos hayachid. You can't carry from a רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid that is not part of your עירוב eiruv into
one that is. So if you draw water, the water at the
bottom is part in their courtyard, part in yours, and it's always
moving around. So you're going to be taking stuff from their courtyard
into yours on שבת; Shabbos; you can't draw water from it on
שבת. Shabbos. Okay, that's what it says. אלא אם כן, Ela im
kein, but here's the way you can do it. Unless what you
did was עשה לו מחיצה עשרה טפחים בין מלמעלה בין מלמטה, asah
lo mechitza asarah tefachim bein mi-lemala bein mi-lemata, unless you made a
מחיצה mechitza in the well, whether high up or below, בין בתוך
אוגנו, bein be-toch ogno, whether right underneath
the lip, which means what, we'll do a different view of it.
Okay, we'll view a, let's see how I'm going to show this.
Okay,
here's your well, looks like a bucket. Anyway, okay, there's the well,
there's the water
at the bottom. Okay, and this sets the dividing line between the
courtyards; like that's one courtyard, this is courtyard A, this is courtyard
B.
Okay, people get the picture?
Now there's a wall, naturally there's a wall between the courtyard. So
naturally there's a wall that goes like this, and the wall actually
goes over the well. Okay, so that's the scenario. So it says
that's not good enough that there's a wall over the well. If
you want to draw water from this on שבת, Shabbos, you have
to make actually a wall hanging in the well itself. Whether it's
below, right next to the water, whether it's above, right under the
lip, the wall has to be in the well itself, then we'll
view it as though the wall goes down and separates the water,
but otherwise the wall up here doesn't work. Now you will say,
what is the difference? The wall is still not at the bottom
of the well, it's not in the water. Either way, whether it's
here or here, you're still saying that we envision it as though
it goes all the way down. Okay, so what difference does it
make? Why not use the wall on top? So the answer is
because the חזל, Chazal, look, water we take water totally for granted
but anybody that's ever followed things that are happening in developing countries,
you know, and in ישראל Yisrael too, of course, but I mean
I don't just mean the rainfall water, I mean just the ability
to get water to where you are. Right, we take that indoor
plumbing completely for granted, you know, obviously in the time of חזל
Chazal it was a major thing to have access to water. So
what they said was on שבת Shabbos they they made particular leniencies
to allow you to access water on שבת. Shabbos. So one classic
example is you've got a body of water below,
you're at your house, you know, whatever, right on or an apartment
building, or you're on a ship too, also, anyway it's right by
the water, you have a body of water below, okay, how do
you draw water from it? That's a כרמלית, karmelis, you're in a
רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. What you do is you have your balcony
and you make a little
רשות היחיד reshus hayachid sort of box on your balcony, and we
envision it as though it goes all the way down into the
water and becomes a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid in the water. so
you can lower your bucket through this box and draw the water.
Okay, so those are special leniencies we do to envision a walls
going down and creating a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid in the water
to allow you to have access to the water. And the phrase
for this is
קלו הוא
שהתירו חכמים במים.
kalu hu shehitiru chachamim
bamayim. Okay, they allow you to view walls going down and be
lenient in order to give you access to water. So, we will
say that by I should use a different color. We will say
that if you make a wall specifically for the purpose of the
water. If you go ahead and make a wall for access to
water, right, then we'll say, oh, we'll be lenient, we'll view it
as though the walls go all the way down and therefore to
give you access to water. But this wall is not made for
access to water and therefore we're not going to apply that lenient
principle up here, even though we will apply it over here. Okay,
is that clear? So that's why the משנה mishna says you can
do it if the wall is within the well, like we let
you do it by making a little, you know, hut out on
your balcony if it's specifically for the purpose of getting access to
the water, we'll give you that leniency.
I should have brought the picture book for עירובין Eruvin for this.
Exactly. Okay, so רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel אומר,
omer, now רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says,
no, he says this is a debate of בית שמאי Beis Shammai
and בית הלל. Beis Hillel. בית שמאי אומרים מלמעלה, Beis Shammai omrim
milma'ala, בית שמאי Beis Shammai
says you can have the wall even high up, meaning not above
the well, but in the well near the lip. ובית הלל אומרים
מלמטה, u'Beis Hillel omrim milmata, you can only have the wall right
near the water. It's not good if it's high up. So that
would make בית הלל Beis Hillel the מחמיר, machmir, and that's a
little strange because this isn't listed in one of the things where
בית הלל Beis Hillel is מחמיר. machmir. So if you look at
תוספות, Tosafos, he says בית שמאי אומרים מלמעלה ובית הלל אומרים מלמטה,
Beis Shammai omrim milma'ala u'Beis Hillel omrim milmata, בכל הספרים גרסינן איפכא
בפרק ק''ט משבת. bechol hasefarim garsinan ipcha beperek kof-tes mishabbat. So in
עירובין, Eruvin, in all of the manuscripts, as תוספות Tosafos says, the
גרסא girsa was the opposite, that בית שמאי Beis Shammai was the
מחמיר machmir and said the wall had to be by the water
and בית הלל Beis Hillel was the מקיל meikil and said the
wall could even be higher up in the well. Okay, so he
says this is a debate of בית שמאי Beis Shammai and בית
הלל Beis Hillel whether it can be high up in the well.
אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, now רב יהודה Rav Yehuda has
the interesting position for us. לא תהא מחיצה גדולה מן הכותל שביניהם.
lo tehei mechitza gedola min hakosel shebeinehem. This wall, why does this
wall have better powers than this big wall up here? If it
works for the water in here, it should work for the wall
up here. So meaning, what is רב יהודה Rav Yehuda saying? רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda is saying I don't need a special leniency by
water. I think, says רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, you can use this
wall to envision it going all the way down, which leads to
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda there's a general principle that a wall can
extend down. Do people see that? That was the purpose of all
of this. Because whatever you say in here, that's a special water
הלכה. halacha. Okay, but רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says even the wall
up here works, which means רב יהודה Rav Yehuda thinks a general
principle is a wall that's suspended over your ground floor, because this
is the relevant ground floor here, the bottom of the well, that
a wall that is suspended can go all the way down, even
as a general special הלכה halacha without being made particularly as a
leniency for water. And therefore that seems to correspond to what's going
on in our משנה, mishna, the debate of a suspended wall. So
let's take a look. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so says look, this
is the debate. The same way רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says over
there by שבת Shabbos a suspended wall works as a general principle,
that's רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi who says a suspended wall works by
סוכה. Sukka. So that's the debate, it's the same position. אמר רבה
בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar
Rabbi Yochanan, so רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar bar Chana says
in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, רב יהודה בשיטת רבי
יוסי אמרה. Rav Yehuda b'shitat Rabbi Yosi amra. Look, there רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda in the discussion in עירובין Eruvin is רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi in our משנה, mishna, דאמר מחיצה תלויה מתרת, de'amar mechitza teluya
materes, that a suspended מחיצה mechitza works. So that's you know, again,
מתרת materes is more of an עירובין Eruvin שבת Shabbos word, but
that's רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yosi position, that's רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda position,
it's the same position. הגמרא haGemara says ולא היא. v'lo hi. הגמרא
haGemara says no, not necessarily. You might say it works for שבת
Shabbos and not for סוכה, Sukka, it works for סוכה Sukka and
not
for שבת. Shabbos. Why, what's the logic behind that? לא רב יהודה
סבר לה כרבי יוסי, lo Rav Yehuda savar lah k'Rabbi Yosi, he
wouldn't hold with רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi that it would work for
סוכה. Sukka. עד כאן לא קאמר רב יהודה התם אלא בעירובי חצירות
דרבנן. ad kan lo ka'amar Rav Yehuda hatam ela b'eruvei chatzeiros d'rabbanan.
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda is only willing to say that for an
עירוב חצירות eruv chatzeiros purpose, right? It's not like it was a
biblical question. Both of them were רשות היחיד reshus hayachid without this.
It was only a question of allowing you to draw water from
the well. It was only a rabbinic problem of taking an object
from one רשות היחיד reshus hayachid to another רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid.
So fine, for rabbinic purposes he'll let the he'll say a suspended
wall will work. אבל הכא סוכה דאורייתא, aval hacha Sukka d'oraisa, but
here that you're dealing with a biblical question, a סוכה. Sukka. Wow,
he wouldn't allow this. He'll allow a suspended wall for rabbinic issues,
not for biblical ones. That's why he wouldn't necessarily agree by
סוכה. sukkah. ולא רבי יוסי סבר כרבי יהודה, velo Rebbe Yose savar
k'Rebbe Yehuda, and רבי יוסי Rebbe Yose won't necessarily hold like רבי
יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda. עד כאן לא קאמר רבי יוסי הכא, ad kan
lo ka'amar Rebbe Yose hacha, רבי יוסי Rebbe Yose only says it
works by סוכה sukkah why?
אלא בסוכה דמצות עשה, ela b'sukkah d'mitzvas aseh, cause at the end
of the day, the worst עבירה aveira you could do in terms
of הלכות סוכה hilchos sukkah is not be מקיים mikayeim your עשה.
aseh. Right? You could do everything wrong and at the end of
the day, I'm not going to let the יום טוב yom tov
of סוכה, sukkah, you know, but the sort of מצוה, mitzvah, סוכה
sukkah and לולב lulav is you wouldn't have done your מצות עשה
mitzvas aseh as opposed to שבת. Shabbos. שבת, Shabbos, it's a world
full of big עבירות. aveiros. Okay, so says אבל שבת דסקילה
לא, aval Shabbos d'skila lo, שבת Shabbos where there's a lot of
you're punishable by death, it's big עבירות aveiros by שבת, Shabbos, even
though this is a דרבנן d'rabbanan application, we should be very strict
in the laws of שבת. Shabbos. So in the end of the
day, the גמרא gemara does not have, you know, what I think
could have been a more interesting conceptual difference between שבת Shabbos and
סוכה. sukkah. Right? If you wanted to say there's a difference between
שבת Shabbos and סוכה, sukkah, you might want to say, well, by
סוכה sukkah it's not just about a מחיצה, mechitzah, it's about being
a wall, maybe there's a different status about being of a wall
than a סוכה. sukkah. If you want your סוכה sukkah to be
considered a habitable space, maybe it has to go all the way
to the ground to be considered habitable. You could have made a
conceptual distinction between the two. The גמרא gemara just says the distinction
just could be how stringent or lenient it is. So we might
consider the שבת Shabbos case more lenient and allow it there because
it's only a דרבנן. d'rabbanan. We might consider the סוכה sukkah case
more lenient because it's a world of and only a מצות עשה
mitzvas aseh and not a world of איסור סקילה. issur skila. So
you could פסקן pasken it in one case not the other because
of stringency leniency, but again, it would have been interesting to explore
that maybe it's different because maybe the criteria are fundamentally different, particularly
the idea that סוכה sukkah to be the מחיצה mechitzah has to
be more functional in order to make it a habitable space, that
might have more demanded that you don't just use a suspended מחיצה.
mechitzah. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara continues. ואי תימא מעשה שנעשה
בציפורי על פי מי נעשה, v'im toma ma'aseh shenasah b'Tzipori al pi
mi na'asah, one minute, we're going to tell you about a story
about
a famous story that happened in ציפורי, Tzipori, which you'll find out
about in a minute. Now ציפורי, Tzipori, as we all know, I'm
teasing, is רבי יוסי's Rebbe Yose town. Okay, רבי יוסי Rebbe Yose
was the גדול gadol of ציפורי. Tzipori. So now and we're going
to have a story on שבת Shabbos where they a thing happened
in ציפורי Tzipori and they used a suspended מחיצה mechitzah to let
them carry. Okay, now the גמרא gemara assumes this is good evidence
that רבי יוסי Rebbe Yose about סוכה sukkah would apply his law
by שבת, Shabbos, because the רבי יוסי Rebbe Yose in our משנה
mishnah says a suspended wall works by סוכה sukkah and there's this
famous story in ציפורי Tzipori that they used a suspended wall to
carry on שבת. Shabbos. So you see רבי יוסי Rebbe Yose does
use his principle of סוכה sukkah to apply it to שבת. Shabbos.
So על פי מי נעשה? al pi mi na'asah? No, on whose
authority was that done? לא על פי רבי יוסי, lo al pi
Rebbe Yose, that was not done on רבי יוסי's Rebbe Yose authority.
אלא על פי רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי, ela al pi Rebbe Yishmael
b'Rebbe Yose, it was his son whose authority was. רבי יוסי Rebbe
Yose had already passed away and his son was the one who
gave the ruling in ציפורי. Tzipori. So you cannot prove that רבי
יוסי Rebbe Yose would have applied the same principle in both cases.
Maybe his son applied the principle in both cases, but רבי יוסי
Rebbe Yose we only know applies it in סוכה, sukkah, maybe not
by שבת. Shabbos. Now we're going to see the story of ציפורי,
Tzipori, which is a very fun story. ומה מעשה, u'mah ma'aseh, what
was the story? דכי אתא רב דימי, d'chi ata Rav Dimi, when
רב דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אמר, amar,
he said. פעם אחת שכחו ולא הביאו ספר תורה מערב שבת, pa'am
achas shachachu v'lo heviu sefer Torah m'erev Shabbos, one day they forgot
and they did not bring the ספר תורה sefer Torah from before
שבת Shabbos into the house in the courtyard that they were going
to use as a שול. shul. And that's a big problem, because
how do you get the ספר תורה sefer Torah to where it
has to go? Okay, now the issue again is by the way
not the way רש"י Rashi explains it, is not a דאורייתא d'oraisa
problem but a דרבנן d'rabbanan problem, a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid problem.
He says imagine you've got the following scenario, right? You've got your
מבוי, mavoi, which is your basically your street, okay, and out from
your מבוי mavoi comes various courtyards, and each courtyard has houses, okay,
and basically what you had here was was that the ספר תורה
sefer Torah was in this house and the בית כנסת beis knesses
was over here, the other side of the מבוי. mavoi. Now normally,
right, if the מבוי mavoi had was a dead end מבוי mavoi
and whatever, normally, you know, you could carry if it's a רשות
היחיד, reshus hayachid, except it's you want to carry into the מבוי,
mavoi, you've have to make a שיתוף מבואות. shituf mevo'os. You need
דרבנן d'rabbanan everybody to come together, shared loaf of bread, same idea
of carrying in the courtyard. Okay, you didn't do it. So what
are they going to do? Right? You can't make a שיתוף מבואות
shituf mevo'os on שבת. Shabbos. So you could say that everybody should
go over there to דאוון, davon, but okay, maybe it was too
small. So anyway, what they did was they put up curtains from
one house to the next. Now how did that work? It's already
a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, how does that help? It helps because
the reason a מבוי mavoi is no good is because it has
multiple the ones that have the שול shul and the בית כנסת.
beis knesses. There are no other houses that enter into that space.
So it's not a public type of a space that needs a
שיתוף. shituf. And so that's how the walls now allow them to
carry the ספר תורה sefer torah from one space to the next.
Okay? Isn't this creating a, an עירוב eruv at this point? Right,
right. Meaning how, are you really allowed to create a רשות היחיד
reshus hayachid and to put up walls? So the גמרא Gemara will
ask that question, okay? Let's take, let's take a look. But, but
that's what you went ahead and did. So, so למחר, lemachar, the
next day, פירשו סדינים על גבי העמודים, pirsu sadinim al gabei ha'amudim,
they spread out, you know, cloths on, on posts. Apparently they had
posts. והביאו ספר תורה וקראו בו, vehevi'u sefer torah vekar'u vo, and
they brought the ספר תורה sefer torah and read from it. So
the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so that was the story. So the
first חידוש chiddush is for some reason the גמרא Gemara assumes that
these sheets are suspended off the ground more than three טפחים, tefachim,
right? Because that's why, why it brought it into the discussion. Why
it assumes that, who knows? I mean, maybe they just knew the
story and the story was that they were suspended high. So the
relevance of this, remember, is that, ah, you see this case, those
things were suspended, they allowed you to carry. That's the position that
a suspended מחיצה mechitzah works. It's רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi by סוכה
Sukkah applied to
the שבת Shabbos case.
Okay, so that was the relevance. But now the גמרא Gemara is
going to say, fine, put the מחיצה תלויה mechitzah tluyah issue aside.
Let's see how they really managed to do this. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this. פירשו סלקא דעתך? pirsu salka daitach? Did they
literally, how could you say they spread the, the curtains? מהיכן הביאו
בשבת? me'heichan hevi'u beShabbos? Where'd they bring them from? אלא, ela, right,
meaning how do they get the curtains there to begin with? You
can't carry in that space. So how did they get the curtains
to start? So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא, ela, rather, you have
to say, מצאו סדינים פרוסים על גבי עמודים והביאו ספר תורה וקראו
בו. matzu sadinim perusim al gabei amudim vehevi'u sefer torah vekar'u vo.
They found that there, that there was actually these things spread on
a curtain and, and therefore they carried it, which is a little
bit funny because they found a perfect thing exactly the way they
needed it. But maybe it means that they moved them. Like, maybe
they found the stuff, but also moving it, how do you move
it if you don't have a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and so,
if you don't have. So it's a little bit funny now that
we've sort of have described, like, oh, they discovered it all set
up. Which actually, we're going to, the discussion that we're having here
about because earlier the opinion was that the wall that was there,
you didn't need to extend down because on שבת Shabbos you could
intellectually extend it down, right? So this could be like they didn't
have כוונה kavanah to create a מחיצה. mechitzah. Somebody hung up their
laundry. Right, right, but it raises the question. Well, I'm going to
get to that issue about כוונה kavanah in a minute. But I
want so, but, but yes, I'll get back to that in a
minute. But I want to say first another thing about what the
גמרא'ס Gemara's question was. רש"י Rashi says the גמרא'ס Gemara's question was,
how did they get the cloths there? תוספות Tosafos says, that's not
a problem. You're creative. You don't have a מחיצה, mechitzah, how would
you get, you know, some type of a cloth from one place
to another? Let's say, what could you use that you could get
from one place to another? Your, if the, the post, supposed to
be a מקום פטור? makom patur? No, no, no. Your clothes. You're
just wearing. Why don't you just wear some big shawl, walk over
there, and then take the shawl off and spread it. It's not
a problem of how they got it there. So תוספות Tosafos says,
the problem is, as was as we're saying and there's actually a
גרסא girsa that says, how are you allowed to do this? You're
making an אהל ohel on שבת. Shabbos. Now, you're not making an
אהל ohel in the sense of a roof, right, that's been our
focus of אהל, ohel, but you're making part of a building, you're
making the walls of a building. So that was the question, not
how did they get the curtains there. How'd they spread the curtains,
right, that was your question, right, how'd they spread the curtains and
make a halachic wall and make a wall on שבת. Shabbos. Okay,
fine, they found curtains already spread. Okay, which is a little bit
again, you know, hard to understand, you know, they discovered exactly things
spread the way they need them. Maybe it's like your point, somebody
had laid out their laundry and they say, hey, wait a minute,
we can use this laundry line here. Even if you don't, you
wind up doing that on שבת, Shabbos, right? Wait, we got this
fence, we got a bush over there, we got a, okay, it
works. So maybe that, that's a good explanation of what it means
to say they found. They figured out that they could use that.
And that also laundry would be a good example of מחיצה תלויה.
mechitzah tluyah. You have to have like big cloaks or whatever, you
know, on your laundry. Okay, so that's the explanation. That, by the
way, is a very important question of are you allowed to make
a מחיצה mechitzah on שבת? Shabbos? Because רש"י Rashi says, he, רש"י
Rashi crossed out the גרסא girsa that said, how are you allowed
to make, to make אהל ohel on שבת? Shabbos? He says, of
course you can. It's a מחיצה. mechitzah. מחיצה Mechitzah isn't an אהל.
ohel. אהל Ohel needs a roof. רש"י Rashi crossed out that גרסא.
girsa. According to רש"י, Rashi, you can make walls on שבת. Shabbos.
Okay, not with mortar and, you know, what brick, but whatever, you
can hang things up. תוספות Tosafos says no, it's a problem. But
תוספות Tosafos acknowledges that there are other גמרות Gemaras that sound like
it is okay to make a wall on שבת. Shabbos. What's the
difference? And תוספות Tosafos introduces a very important principle in הלכות שבת
hilchos Shabbos that you cannot make, it's not you can't make any
wall, you could like suspend the something for I don't know, you
have a nice tapestry and you want to suspend it on a
line and look at it or whatever. You want to even use
it as, you want to create a private space, you want to
change in an area. So you spread out these cloths so it's
like a private space so you can change, you know, you can
change. Privacy, all that, that's fine to make walls on שבת. Shabbos.
What you can't do is you can't make a wall that הלכתית
halachically serves the הלכתי halachic purpose of a wall. You can't make
something a מחיצה המתיר, mechitzah hamattir, a מחיצה mechitzah that makes the
space permissible. That's more of an effective status change of what that
wall is doing and that's what's אסורה. assurah. So here, because the
מחיצה mechitzah made the space permissible, that's the type of wall you're
not allowed to make. I'll just read you the one sentence in
תוספות Tosafot that says that. He says like this, he says, if
you take a look, four lines in תוספות Tosafot or five lines
before the lines get to be the medium size, the word לרבינו
תם. le-Rabbeinu Tam. Do you see that? So he says, ונראה לרבינו
תם דמינא צד נמי שייך עשיית אהל, ve-nireh le-Rabbeinu Tam di-mina tzad
nami shayach asiyat ohel, a wall can also be an אהל, ohel,
וכהאי גוונא דמחיצה זו מועלת להתיר, ve-che-hai gavna de-mechitzah zo moelet le-hattir,
when the מחיצה mechitzah serves the function of making the space permissible
in a הלכתי halachic way and that's why it was made, not
just it happens to do that, then חשיב עשיית אהל בתחילה, chashiv
asiyat ohel bat-tchilah, that is the problem. So you can't make a
wall to serve a הלכתי halachic function. You can make a wall
to serve another function on שבת. Shabbos. That's actually how we פסקן.
pasken. Yes. And yet, I think people putting up מחיצות mechitzot in
שבת Shabbos in order to דאוון. daven. Right. So that is, that
works because we say that the function of a מחיצה mechitzah for
דאוונינג davening is more functional. It's like the privacy scenario I gave
you before. So it allows you to דאוון, daven, but it doesn't
הלכתית halachically create that idea of a different type of a space.
Okay. The problem is when the wall is there to הלכתית halachically
make a status change in terms of the nature of the space,
whereas that type of a מחיצה mechitzah for דאוונינג, davening, the way
it's allowed on שבת, Shabbos, is that we emphasize it's basically there
just to create privacy. Okay. The reality of upgrading privacy is it
does allow you to דאוון, daven, but that's its function and its
function isn't הלכתית halachically to serve... If it was הלכתית halachically to
serve as a מחיצה, mechitzah, you would only need עשרה טפחים asarah
tefachim and you wouldn't need it to go higher. So it's actually
interesting. People that are... there are some people that use a עשרה
טפחים asarah tefachim מחיצה. mechitzah. There are some שולס shuls that still
do. A few OU שולס shuls still use עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim
מחיצה. mechitzah. And that would be... so if you only use a
עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim מחיצה, mechitzah, you can't make it on שבת
Shabbos because then you're applying it to the normal laws of מחיצה
mechitzah and that is actually a problem. Yes. Yeah, Rabbi Mel Sacks
told me that he heard personally from הרב סולובייצ'יק Rav Soloveitchik that
the מחיצה mechitzah had to be עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim high and
I saw Rabbi Yehuda Herzl Henkin publicly say that... Yes, הרב הנקין
Rav Henkin says... הרב הנקין Rav Henkin says עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim
is really sufficient. But he also... he also said it can't be
a fabric מחיצה. mechitzah. Well, it can't be suspended off the ground.
He has exactly this issue. If you want to make the מחיצה
mechitzah for דאוונינג davening into a classic הלכתי halachic מחיצה, mechitzah, it
has leniencies and stringencies. Right. Okay, so let's keep... let's continue. הגמרא
The Gemara says like this. Okay. Oh, by the way, one other
final interesting side point I should make is I was doing some
reading on ancient synagogues. I mean, if you have the patience for
it, there's this great book that has everything. It's called... is it
called The Synagogue or something or Ancient Synagogue? And it's like 800
pages thick. It's by Lee Levine. It has... not Lee Levine... Lee
Levine? Might be by... I think Lee Levine. Anyway, it has absolutely
everything about ancient synagogues. Anyway, so it's interesting that the older synagogues,
there was no place for the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. Old, you
know, only sort of like, I don't know how old, third century,
fourth century, did they start being an ארון Aron and a place
for ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. So it's actually... and some of the
interesting literary evidence... I mean, that's clear from the architectural evidence, although
I might have the centuries off. But some of the literary evidence
to that is a story like this: they didn't bring the ספר
תורה Sefer Torah from ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, which means that they
naturally kept the ספר תורה Sefer Torah in a different space than
the שול. shul. And we don't find any evidence of ארונות aronot
in the שול shul except for, you know, except in sort of
a later period, later maybe תנאי Tannaic period, not super late, but
you know, not in an earlier period. Okay. So הגמרא the Gemara
says like this: אמר רב חסדא אמר אבימי מחצלת ארבעה ומשהו מתרת
בסוכה משום דופן. Amar Rav Chisda amar Avimi machzelet arbaah u-mashehu materet
be-sukkah mishum dofen. So remember I just told you before about the
question about going both ways? He's going to have it go both
ways, but with לבוד, lavud, not with extending because we don't פסקן
pasken like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. We say you cannot do a
suspended wall. But if you have a mat that is ארבעה טפחים
arbaah tefachim wide, four and a little bit, you can be... that's
good for your סוכה. sukkah. Here's your exact עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim
סוכה. sukkah. And what you're going to do is you're going to
make a mat that is four and a half, go right over
here, and right in the middle. So between that and the ground
is, right, it's 2.9 טפחים, tefachim, and that to the top is
2.9, right? So combined, you do the math, right three three whatever
six right and the extra half covers up the point one and
therefore you've got your whole ten טפחים. tefachim. So you basically do
a לבוד lavud to the bottom and a לבוד lavud to the
top and maybe we have to do it more like that, right,
and therefore you can do the whole סוכה sukkah with a with
a mat that is ארבע arba טפחים tefachim wide okay or a
little more than ארבע arba טפחים tefachim because לבוד lavud is a
little less than three. מחצלת ארבעה ומשהו machatzelet arba'ah umashehu four and
a little bit מתרת את הסוכה—where matert et hasukkah am I?—מתרת את
הסוכה matert et hasukkah משום דופן mishum dofen as a wall. היכי
עביד heichi avid how how do you do it? תולהו באמצע tolehu
be'emtza you put it smack in the middle of the wall assuming
an exact ten טפח tefach סוכה. sukkah. פחות משלושה למטה פחות משלושה
למעלה pachot mishlosha lemata pachot mishlosha lemala within a little less than
three טפחים tefachim off of the ground and a little less than
three טפחים tefachim off of the סכך s'chach וכל פחות משלוש כלבוד
דמי vechol pachot mishalosh kelavud dami you get to say לבוד lavud
in both ways and you have your wall. Says פשיטא pshita isn't
that obvious? מהו דתימא mahu deteima חד לבוד אמרינן תרי לבוד לא
אמרינן chad lavud amrinan trei lavud lo amrinan I might say you
can say one לבוד lavud you can't do it at both ends.
קמשמע לן kamashma lan that you're able to do both. We will
see later how often you can how much you can use multiple
ones on top of one another but here anyway they're at opposite
ends and therefore it works. מיתיבי meitivei I'll ask him on this
מחצלת שבעה ומשהו מתרת בסוכה משום דופן machatzelet shiva umashehu materes basukkah
mishum dofen we have a ברייתא baraisa that says you need it
to be seven and a bit presumably you can only use one
לבוד lavud you can't use two לבוד. lavud. לא lo says no.
כי תניא ההיא בסוכה גדולה ki tanya hahi besukkah gedola that's talking
about a big סוכה sukkah ומאי קמשמע לן umai kamashma lan what's
it teaching us? דמשלשלים דפנות מלמעלה למטה כרבי יוסי demishalshilin defanos milamala
lemata kerabi yosi like רבי יוסי rabbi yosi meaning when would you
need a mat seven you'd need a mat seven if your סוכה
sukkah looks like this. Okay you can't say לבוד lavud at both
ends okay but you put it up here and you say לבוד
lavud up here then you have so if it's seven right if
it's seven and a half and you're saying לבוד lavud then you
got ten טפחים tefachim and then but then you have to extend
it down and that would only follow with רבי יוסי. rabbi yosi.
So according to the ברייתא baraisa that says seven and a bit
that's assuming it's a big סוכה. sukkah. If you put it down
here everybody by the way would agree that it's good and there's
one גרסא girsa that רש"י rashi says has of the גמרא gemara
like that that it's not about רבי יוסי rabbi yosi if you
put it down here you said לבוד lavud and then it extends
all the way up. You use לבוד lavud plus גוד אסיק gud
asik you see that? Right? You see that? You use לבוד lavud
to give you ten and once you have a wall then you
say גוד אסיק. gud asik. Okay so that's the easier case. But
our גרסא girsa of the גמרא gemara says maybe we're even talking
about a bigger חידוש chiddush that you put it up here you
said לבוד lavud and then you said גוד אחית gud achis but
that is only רבי יוסי rabbi yosi would say that because that
is the idea of a מחיצה mechitzah suspended off of the ground.
Okay so that would be the חידוש chiddush of the ברייתא baraisa
of seven and a bit. Let's just finish to the end of
the דף. daf. אמר רב יוסף amar rav yosef פס ארבעה ארבעה.
pas arba'ah arba'ah. Now a מחצלת machatzelet a mat means something that
is running sort of widthwise and they were doing it you know
off of the סכך s'chach and off of the ground. He talks
about a פס pas which also talks about a plank of wood
but somehow that signifies something that's going vertically. Okay? So you have
a vertical plank of wood that's ארבעה טפחים ומשהו arba'ah tefachim umashehu
and a bit מתיר בסוכה משום דופן matir basukkah mishum dofen that
works because what is the minimum you know size of each you
know length and width of a סוכה? sukkah? What's a סוכה? sukkah?
If people paying attention? Seven by seven טפחים. tefachim. So if you
have basically a סוכה sukkah that is right a seven טפח tefach
wall and what you went ahead and did is you put a
mat here—that's not I'm not good at this anyway—you had whatever anyway
you put a mat that's four and a half and it's within—that's
why you have to do like—ah! You have one wall here okay
and you have let's say a little bit of another wall you
have your one ומשהו umashehu and where is going but now what
you did for your for your critical second wall is you put
a fencing four and a half here four ומשהו umashehu just calling
it a half. Well if it's within three טפחים tefachim 2.9 you
can say לבוד lavud attached the total is more than seven or
is seven and now you've got your two walls ומשהו umashehu okay
and therefore it's good. So מתיר בסוכה משום דופן ומוקמי לה בפחות
משלושה טפחים סמוך לדופן matir basukkah mishum dofen umokmi la bapachot mishlosha
tefachim samuch ladofen you put it within three טפחים tefachim of the
wall וכל פחות משלושה טפחים כלבוד דמי vechol pachot mishlosha tefachim kelavud
dami and then it works by לבוד. lavud. מאי קמשמע לן mai
kamashma lan so what's the חידוש? chiddush? הא קמשמע לן ha kamashma
lan the חידוש chiddush is שיעור משך סוכה קטנה שבעה shiur meshech
sukkah ketana shiva that the minimum size of a סוכה sukkah is
seven טפחים. tefachim. Okay? Funny way of teaching me the minimum size
of a סוכה sukkah is seven טפחים tefachim but that's the basic
חידוש chiddush that is embedded in that הלכה. halacha. All right.